[Music]
hello and welcome to Dynamics 365 uh
field service integration session my
name is Ivan ktic and I'm a product
manager in business Central team at
Microsoft so in this session I will take
you through a sort of a new kit on the
Block in terms of integration that's the
integration with Dynamics 365 uh field
service between Dynamics 365 field
service and business
Central um this is our agenda for today
we we'll talk a bit about uh the field
service uh integration value what it
brings uh to the table we'll talk about
how do you uh enable this
integration uh how to synchronize uh the
basic Master data that is needed such as
project task resources service items how
to manage work orders and how to consume
them and in the end uh how to uh invoice
the work that has been done uh through
the work orders in uh field service
through business
Central let's first talk a bit about um
what is actually the value and why it is
important that business Central has an
integration to field service uh one of
the things that we hear from uh a lot of
companies and I assume there is no
service company that doesn't want to
streamline their uh service operations
and improve efficiency uh one of the
things that's particularly interested in
here for our business Central customers
and partners is the capability of uh
providing visual scheduling of uh of the
work increasing Automation and
aligning uh the work order data to with
financial uh transactions uh in business
Central on the other hand what business
Central actually brings in here is that
visibility to the uh inventory of uh the
products uh that you have but on the
other hand uh one of the things uh where
field service actually also brings a ton
of value is uh a lot of uh is offline
capabilities where you can find
technicians and people usually working
in places where they don't have uh uh
internet connection so this is something
that uh field service will nicely
supplement uh to the value that business
Central is uh providing on top of that U
business Central uh brings in U accurate
and compliant invoicing uh to the mix
together with uh ensuring that you have
uh consistent product and resource
information be it prices be it costs and
so on another very important thing to
notice in terms of uh integration value
is uh as you all know we do have uh
integration to data ver and Dynamics 365
for sales and our integration Solutions
are built in a way that they can be
easily customized and extended by
partners and some of the partners might
have uh endeavored uh in in this way of
uh creating a custom uh solutions that
integrate uh field service but now that
is no longer uh needed as you get uh you
get these capabilities of the page which
of course uh helps red reduce the burden
uh on the partner Channel and given that
this is now part of uh part of the
product and of course it also will
hopefully reduce the implementation time
that is needed from what I've been
hearing from months to maybe uh couple
of
weeks so let's dive in uh the first uh
sort of section of the field service
integration in order for you to use the
field service integration of course you
will need to uh enable it
as I mentioned we have data worse and
Dynamics 365 for sales uh integration
already and the field service
integration is something that builds on
top this means that in order for you to
enable field service integration you
will first need to enable a connection
to a data verse environment where you
have sales and field service installed
all of this is actually packaged up in a
assisted setup uh guide which will guide
you through uh through this uh through
this process process in order to enable
field service integration you will also
need to uh designate some uh project
Journal templates and batches where the
data about the consumption uh of hours
and consumption of products is going to
land in business Central once the
integration is uh enabled apart from
that uh it's important that you also
specify how and when you want uh the
consumption that happens in field
service uh to get transferred to to
Business Center so you have two options
of uh when to U when to synchronize uh
work orders or products you can actually
choose between when uh when those are
actually marked as used in field service
on on the product lines and you also
have an option uh to uh to set uh when
and how you want this data that gets
transferred to the project journals to
be posted whether it gets posted
automatically or you want to have some
more control and you just want that data
to land in your project journals then
you review it and post it uh
manually which brings us to uh our first
demo so one of the first things uh that
you need to do is we need to look at the
field service uh settings uh the reason
why we need to uh change some of these
settings is because they will conflict
with the way that the integration is
working working one of the first things
that to do is to make sure that the
inbuilt uh invoicing capabilities of
field service are uh disabled so we
disable uh work order invoice creation
another thing that you will uh want to
turn off is calculating prices and costs
because business Central is going to be
the product uh that when integrated is
going to drive those things and on the
purchase tab U since we'll be using
inventory from business uh Central uh
you should actually set use products out
of stock to uh
blank so now back in business Central
when we start the field service
integration setup as I said you need to
pick uh project Journal templates you
need to pick the project uh Journal
batch you will also need to designate a
uh hour unit of measure because all of
the work in uh field service is
expressed in duration so we need to know
what is going to be the uh unit of
measure for that and you will pick this
uh work order product synchronization
and posting uh posting settings uh in uh
assisted setup after the assisted setup
is uh completed you can actually go and
run the full
synchronization and that will actually
uh get you uh transfer all the data uh
that uh that is needed
for uh for integration uh to
work you simply go and select you
synchronize everything and once that
process is completed uh you'll be able
to uh start working with uh field
service
integration so in this demo we briefly
looked at uh what are the field service
settings that are needed and how to
actually enable uh the field service
integration so let's move
forward the the next section of U of the
session talks about the master data that
needs to be synchronized and you saw us
run the uh run full synchronization
which initiates uh some of the new uh
Master data that gets uh transferred uh
that gets synchronized between business
Central and field service what you may
have noticed uh briefly in here and in
the picture uh that we have in here is
that we are now synchronizing resources
to a bookable resource uh to enable work
order scheduling we also do synchronize
uh service items to uh customer uh to
customer assets uh to track operations
on on uh on such uh assets and we also
do synchronize uh project tasks uh to
sort of enable consumption and to link
the work order to a specific project
that is then going to be where the
postings are going to occur and from
where the invoices are going to be
created and now let's uh also switch to
another demo to see all of that uh in
action so we'll start this demo uh in
field service and one of the things that
you might have noticed is I've mentioned
we are now synchronizing resources to
bookable resources all of you who know
our integration to Dynamics 365 or sales
know that the resources have actually
been synchronized uh to uh
products in order to enable work order
scheduling we need to now start
synchronizing resour is not to the
products but to the bookable resource
one of the things that you will be
warned uh in the during the connection
setup uh to to field service is that if
if the con if the if the assisted setup
guide actually detects that you have
resources synchronized with products it
will actually propose that you un
uncouple them in order to make sure that
the resources can uh get um synchronized
to bookable resource there's another uh
there's another there's another caveat
in using the products that you might
have uh synchronized already with sales
in order to use the products uh that in
order to use the products from business
Central in field service we will need to
make sure that the products have the
field service product type uh uh filled
in the reason why integration is not
doing that out of the box is uh on one
hand performance reasons because you
might have a large catalog of items for
us to do it uh
automatically uh and uh another thing is
the the resource thing that I just
mentioned the resources might be
included in there so for that reason we
actually said it's better to uh it's
better to leave this uh up to the users
because it's fairly easy to U it's
fairly easy to do that especially with
virtual tables and so on I have a small
list of uh I have small list of business
Central products which I know how I want
to uh set this uh field service product
type it actually does map to um business
centrals uh uh business Central items uh
type right so let's just set all of
these products to be inventory and I
have a couple of them that I want to set
as uh service let's take the project fee
as well
and let's just save
that all right so while that is being
done let's switch back to business
Central and look at the integration
table
mappings and in here we can go through
some of these new mappings uh that have
been introduced from what you can see in
here so there are two mappings one for
work order products and one for work
order services that are going to bring
bring in the data from um work orders
that have uh some work executed that
needs to be either consumed or posted in
business Central there are project tasks
if you look at the filters in here we
are looking only at the project tasks of
type posting these are going to be the
ones uh to which you will be able to
link the recorder too and then there is
also uh
resources uh these are the conditions
for the resources that we are syncing as
you can see uh the the resources that we
will be syncing to bable Resource need
to have base unit of measure set to our
that thing that that setting that we've
uh We've Set uh during assisted setup
the resource shouldn't be blocked and
the resources should not uh use uh time
sheets in order to be eligible for uh in
order to be eligible for
syncing and
uh and if we uh if we go and look at the
resource list
hopefully my resources have already
synchronized let me see yes they are as
you can see they are all coupled you
have the standard set of uh actions that
you
are that users are used to from our uh
Dynamics 365 or sales integration so you
can uh go ahead and uh set up coupling
delete coupling do match base coupling
synchronize the data or simply open a u
sort of a couple
uh resource uh directly in in field
service that will start the field
service and you will see the data from
uh from business Central uh being
transferred uh in here okay so switching
back to
resources let's also have a look at uh
uh projects and how they are uh how they
are actually uh linked on Project tasks
so I will have a look at uh the project
task lines and in here if you look at
the uh project task card again you will
see that standard set of actions uh that
are available uh also in our other uh
Integrations to uh for for the coupled
uh for the coupled records so let's open
a project task uh in field service in
here and what you can see what you can
do uh directly from here we could just
go ahead and uh create a new work
order you can see the data from business
Central has uh already been uh
synchronized and let me
just uh let me just
pick workorder type is set and
everything let's go ahead and save the
recorder okay and here we have a uh work
order that has been created using the
business Central data it has been linked
to a business Central um project task
and now it's actually ready to uh add
products and services and book the
resources for it so in this demo U I've
shown you how to uh how to prepare the
products uh or items to work with u with
with field service we've seen uh
resources being synchronized to bookable
Resource and I also shown you project
tasks and uh how to link a how to link
and create a new work order from a
project task so next section of uh of
this session talks about uh how do you
manage uh work orders so as you saw we
created a uh first uh work order uh we
brought in a uh service and billing
accounts uh to work order and it was
fairly easy to uh to link the work order
to a project task you can use the you
can use the path that I've just shown
you or you can simply just create a new
work order and uh pick among the tasks
that belong to a uh specific service and
building accounts or sell to and build
to uh
customers and of course uh what we
didn't see on that work order was uh the
business Central price list also uh gets
uh gets transferred in there and can be
uh picked as something that will drive
the pricing for for that particular
workor
order uh work orders uh have uh work
order products and services this is
where you record uh what kind of uh uh
items uh or products you will need uh to
complete the work order um in business
Central we are uh synchronizing uh uh
items of type inventory and uh
non-inventory items and they can be
picked in workorder product lines you
can also uh you will also be able to see
a quantity on hand for the selected uh
for the selected uh product on the work
called the product line and also uh we
are synchronizing items of type Service
as uh work order uh service
lines after you have Set uh after you
have Set uh the the the material that
you will use and you have estimated U
you've added a service that is going to
be performed another thing that you will
need to do uh in order to proceed with
executing the work order you will need
to book uh some resources what you can
see here on the screen there's a list of
uh well-known uh business Central
resources from which you can actually
pick up uh which you can pick and uh
schedule to perform the work on the work
order and as always there's no better
way than uh seeing that thing uh in
action so let's switch over to a another
demo so we'll start this demo uh back in
field service we've already created a
work order and now it's time to add some
products and services uh to it so we'll
add uh our
airpod coffee maker we'll put in some
estimated
quantity we'll save
this what you can see in here it also
automatically picks up the information
about the inventory from uh business
Central we'll also add some services
if you remember we put these two uh two
items of type service let's call it just
a repair and let's say that we
need uh that will need three uh three
hours that will need three hours for
that now that we have uh now that we
have the product and we have the service
the last thing that remains in order for
this work order to become scheduled is
we need to book some resources and we
will do that from the resource
scheduling
let just go ahead and say we need uh
location agnostic resources and I'll
just turn this
off and here you can actually see the
business Central resources that have
been mapped to bookable Resource which
you can now uh uh book uh for specific
work orders all right so now that we
have a uh booking cre created uh let's
actually go ahead
and relate it in here you can save and
close this and we can now see that the
work order has been moved uh to the
state uh
scheduled okay so in in this demo you've
seen how you can actually add the
products and services that you
synchronized from business Central uh in
field service work order uh you can
create a booking for that and and uh how
you can actually see the uh quantity
coming from uh business Central uh
directly in a work order product uh
line next thing that you want to do now
that we have scheduled the work order um
to be uh workorder and the services to
be executed our technicians go out they
do consume the materials that have been
added to the work order that you consume
uh hours that have been uh put uh on the
work order
and after they are done they will uh
report back after the service has been
uh executed on uh what has what has
happened in order for the accounting
department and for the sales department
to be able to on one hand account for
the costs that have occurred during uh
execution of that uh work order and to
account for the uh inventory and
actually invoice in the end invoice the
the work
order so once we uh once we set the the
workorder product uh uh line uh
workorder products and workorder
services as in a state used we will get
uh this information sent back to uh
business Central in those project
Journal template and the pro Journal
batch uh that we've uh that we've
specified and from there we can proceed
with posting consumption and invoicing
and
recording uh recording these
transactions against that uh uh linked
project task that we put on the work
order so let's see that in a
demo so we'll start this demo back in
the field service where we have a
scheduled uh work order and now as the
technician is executing the work order
he will Mark the workorder product and
the work order service lines as used
let's just accept the
defaults in here and for services we
will also say yes we've actually used
let's say we used actually an hour
rather than 30 minutes to make things
interesting and let's save and close
that as well so back in business Central
we'll look at the project
journal to see that all of the uh used
workorder products and services have
been indeed carried uh through what you
can see is uh three airpods and one hour
one hour of uh repair that has been uh
executed in here so let's go ahead and
post
this perfect and now if we look at
the if you look at the project and the
task that we have actually
uh linked this work order
to we can actually see that uh indeed
these lines have been uh transferred uh
to to that uh specific uh project
planning lines so in this demo you you
you've seen uh how we marked recorder
product and recorder service lines as
used that actually triggered uh the
transfer of of those lines to project
Journal lines which we then used for uh
posting the consumption uh to the
specific uh project task and we ended up
showing uh showing the the the posted uh
the the posted consumption and the lines
uh in the project planning lines that
got created during that uh posting
process the last thing that we have uh
in order to sort of uh wrap up this
whole process is to uh invoice the
workorders and of course uh this is
something that is uh being done uh
directly from business Central where
once you get the
once you get the project planning lines
you can simply create uh an invoice and
uh that invoice that gets created and
posted will be transferred back to uh
transferred back to uh to field service
uh also as an information of um of
completion of of that particular uh
related to that work order and as an
information of completion of the work
order so let's quickly see that uh in a
in a demo so back in business Central
looking at the project Journal lines we
can now go ahead and create a sales
invoice can view that sales invoice that
was created we can go ahead and post
it after posting it we would actually go
ahead and send it to our
customer and of course uh we also have a
sort of a recurring job that would pick
up posted invoices and transfer them to
u to field service or sales but for the
uh for the sake of the demo I will just
click here to have this created so I
think we should actually have an invoice
now done yes and if I click the invoice
in here what you can see is that that
information about the invoice uh
actually goes and gets transferred
together with the products and the
information about the posting back to uh
field
service and in this last demo you've
seen how easy it was to Simply convert
the uh project Journal lines to the
sales invoice post the sales invoice and
transfer the posit sales invoice back to
uh field service thus wrapping up the
the the whole
uh the whole uh
process and that was it uh for this
session I hope you've enjoyed it um if
you have the time and if you are willing
to learn more I strongly recommend you
check out uh these two very related
sessions on what's new in service
management what's new in project
management that that is being delivered
by my colleague uh
Andre and uh of course um if you do have
any questions you want to uh engage in
the conversation um have product suggest
or something make sure to check out some
of these links U and reach out to us uh
with your feedback which is always
welcome and with that I want to thank
you for your time and attention during
this
session